IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Gonso, Harry April 23, 1992, 91-096; 20 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 56 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Harry Gonso attended Indiana University as an undergraduate from 1966 to 1970. He played on the football team and discusses balancing his classes and athletics. Right after graduation, he attended Indiana University School of Law and then went into practice in Indiana. Gonso had remained involved with Indiana University, serving on the board of trustees from 1976 until the time of this interview.
  athlete; attorney; board of trustees member
  Cady, Ed; Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Pinnell, George; Wells, Herman B
  drugs; football; law school; presidential searches; student protests; trees; university funding; Vietnam War
- Grabianowski, Mary July 23, 1992, 91-130; 15 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 38 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Mary Grabianowski attended Indiana University from 1968 to 1972. While there, she served as the first female student body president. She discusses the protests that occurred during her time on campus, the Black Student Union protests, her career in politics and as a teacher after graduation, and the changes that have taken place at Indiana University.
  Black Student Union; Common Cause
  high school teacher
  Bayh, Evan; Helmke, Paul; Udall, Stewart Lee
  Cambodia
  campus protests; student government; university funding; World War II
- Gray, James W. July 24, 1992, 91-131; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 39 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on June 3, 1960, James W. Gray is a 1982 Indiana University alumnus who also graduated from the Indiana University School of Law in Indianapolis in 1985. He recalls his years as a student, especially his involvement in Greek life as a member of Phi Kappa Psi and his participation in campus politics. Gray discusses his role as the vice president of the Indiana University Student Association and his assumption of the student trusteeship on the Indiana University board of trustees. He also speaks about his experiences with various Indiana University courses and the issue of funding. In addition, Gray talks about the merits of prominent figures in the university's history including John Ryan, Herman B Wells, Dick Stoner, and George Pinnell.
  Indiana University Student Association; Phi Kappa Psi
  Pinnell, George; Ryan, John W.; Stoner, Richard B.; Wells, Herman B
  campus politics; curriculum; student trusteeship; university funding
- Gray, Judith F. February 21, 1994, 91-236; 21 pages; 1 tape, 58 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Judith F. Gray, born on June 27, 1942, is a 1966 alumnus of Indiana University. In this interview, she recalls her years as a student at Indiana University. Included are memories of her sorority, Alpha Chi Omega, the assassination of president John F. Kennedy, and athletics at Indiana University. Later in her life, Gray became very active in the alumni association; after holding various chairs in the alumni council, she was elected president of the alumni association. After her presidency, she actively participated in the Woodburn Guild. Some of the Indiana University personalities who figure prominently in Gray's interview are Herman B Wells, Thomas Ehrlich, and John Ryan.
  Alpha Chi Omega; Indiana University Alumni Association; Woodburn Guild
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  Indiana University athletics; John F. Kennedy assassination; sororities
- Gray, Moses W. March 4, 1994, 91-240; 17 pages; 1 tape, 40 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on April 13, 1937, Moses Gray attended Indiana University on a football scholarship from 1957 until approximately 1961. In this interview, he discusses the directions his career has taken, from being a New York Jet to a lifelong career with General Motors, and his continuing involvement with Indiana University. He recalls his years as a student at the university and the racism he experienced as well as the exposure to academic and athletic excellence. He is working in the area of fundraising to promote the development of the Neal Marshall Black Culture Center at Indiana University to increase understanding among students, and between students and professors. Gray also speaks fondly of Herman B Wells and of his own involvement with the Indiana University Foundation.
  General Motors Corporation; Indiana University Foundation; Neal Marshall Black Culture Center; New York Jets
  African-Americans; football; Indiana University athletics; racism; university growth
- Grohsmeyer, Frederick A., Jr. April 16, 1992, 91-094; 18 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Frederick Grohsmeyer, a psychologist and professor who graduated from DePauw University, was born on April 7, 1923. In this interview, he speaks of his days teaching at Earlham College and how this experience led him into active involvement in the creation of Indiana University East. Grohsmeyer discusses the planning and development of Indiana University East, the building and managing of this regional campus, and his views on teaching versus administration. He discusses the positive aspects of Indiana University East and the Indiana University regional campuses, especially their attraction to nontraditional students.
  Earlham College; Indiana University East; Purdue University
  1944 GI Bill; Indiana University regional campuses; nontraditional students
- Gros Louis, Kenneth R.R. May 20, 1992, 91-106; 20 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 56 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1936, Kenneth R.R. Gros Louis was a professor and administrator at Indiana University beginning in 1964. In this interview, he speaks of his experiences at Indiana University. He first came as a member of the English Department and then served several administrative positions, including deanships, and served as chair of the English department. He recalls the university in the turbulent nineteen sixties and the protests relating to the Vietnam War and minority rights. In addition, Gros Louis discusses some of the tension and differences which occurred between the faculty and the administrators. He talks of his experiences under different presidents including Elvis J. Stahr, Joseph Sutton, and John Ryan.
  Frenz, Horst; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee
  African-Americans; Indiana University administration; Indiana University regional campuses; university reorganization; Vietnam War protests
- Hagstrom, StanleyOctober 02, 1996 October 15, 1996, 96-024; 63 pp.; 4 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 235 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Stanley Hagstrom, professor of chemistry and computer science, was born on November 30, 1930 in Lincoln Nebraska. He discusses his time as a student at Iowa State University, his tenure as a chemistry and computer science professor, and a research scientist for Lockheed Research Labs in Palo Alto. He also discusses the difficulties of academic marriages, his wife's career, and retirement.
  Iowa State University; Lockheed Corporation; MIT
  California; Candada; Omaha, NE; Washington, DC
  chemistry professor; computer science professor; researcher; scientist
  Bair, Ed; Bonham, Russ; Davidson, Ernie; Hanson, Bob; Parmenter, Charlie; Schafer, Riley; Shull, Harrison; Weurkert, Ernest
  biochemistry; chemistry; computer science; engineering; graduate education; linguistics; marriage; physics; science; tenure; undergraduate students
- Haley, Thomas R., III June 25, 1992, 91-117; 25 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 79 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1961, Thomas R. Haley III is a 1984 alumnus of Indiana University and 1987 graduate of the Indiana University School of Law at Indianapolis. In this interview, He speaks of his years as a student at Indiana University and his involvement in campus politics. After serving as an Indiana University Student Association senator during his undergraduate years, Haley was appointed to be the student trustee on the Indiana University board of trustees from 1985 to 1987. He discusses the rights and responsibilities of this position and its connection to Indiana state politics. Haley also speaks of the Schools of Law in Bloomington and Indianapolis. Some of the central figures in this interview are Dick Stoner, John Ryan, and Thomas Ehrlich.
  board of trustees; Indiana University School of Law; IUPUI School of Law
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Stoner, Richard B.
  campus politics; Indiana politics; student trusteeship
- Harrell, Charles E. May 22, 1991, 91-062; 23 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 20 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Charles Harrell was born in Bloomington in 1911, was a student at Indiana University from 1929 to 1933, and again from 1934 to 1936, when he attended Indiana University School of Law. Harrell worked for Indiana University in the registrar's office, culminating in being the registrar himself, from 1954 to 1967. Harrell was secretary of the board of trustees from 1967 until his retirement. Harrell also reflects on changes in the university, its administration, and its future.
  board of trustees; Columbia University School of Law; Indiana University School of Law
  board of trustees secretary; registrar; university administrator
  Briscoe, Herman T. "Kay"; Bryan, William Lowe; Cookson, Thomas A.; Stahr, Elvis J.
  golf; Great Depression; student protests; university growth; university physical plant; university registration; World War II
- Hartley, Joseph April 29, 1992, 91-098; 29 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 99 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Joseph Hartley became a full professor at Indiana at the age of 32. He remained with the university for the rest of his career as a professor and also, as the associate dean of faculties and as Vice President and Dean of Academic Affairs. Hartley discusses IUPUI, Indiana's business and law schools, diversity, Indiana University regional campuses, and student protest movements.
  Air Force ROTC; IUPUI; Ivy Tech State College; Ku Klux Klan
  Academic Affairs dean; Academic Affairs vice president; associate dean of faculties; associate research director; business professor; teacher
  Hefner, Ray; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B; Welsh, Matthew E.
  curriculum; diversity; education; female students; graduation; Indiana University regional campuses; law school; quonset huts; retirement; student protests; university finances; Vietnam War
- Helmke, W. Paul, Jr. November 10, 1993, 91-217; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 64 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 24, 1948, Paul Helmke is a 1970 alumnus of Indiana University who later attended Yale Law School. In this interview, he discusses his years as a student at Indiana University and his involvement in campus politics. A former student body president, he speaks of campus unrest during the late nineteen sixties including protests against the Vietnam War, protests against the tuition increase, and the Ballantine Lock-In. In addition, Helmke recalls campus life and his involvement with Greek life and activities at Indiana University. Of special interest are Helmke's stories of his friends and classmates from Yale Law School, Bill and Hillary Clinton.
  Army ROTC; Yale Law School
  Clinton, Hillary Rodham; Clinton, William Jefferson
  Ballantine Lock-In; campus politics; campus protests; draft registration; fraternities; student life; tuition increases; Vietnam War
- Hill, Emita December 3, 1993, 91-227; 20 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 56 minutes; no index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Emita Hill obtained her Ph.D. in French and taught in New York City for many years before taking a position at Indiana University Kokomo. While there, she worked as a professor and eventually became the chancellor. Hill discusses her conversations with Tom Ehrlich, her work at Indiana University Kokomo and that campus's characteristics, finances and funding, and her opinions on the role of women in academia.
  Enhancing Minority Attainment Conference; Indiana University Kokomo; Lehman College; National Endowment for the Humanities
  department chairperson; French professor; university chancellor
  New York, New York
  chancellors; Indiana University regional campuses; university finances; university funding; women in academia
- Hine, Maynard K. June 29, 1992, 91-118; 13 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 42 minutes; no index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Maynard Hine served as chairman of the Oral Pathology and Periodontology of the Indiana University Dental School, Dean of the Dental School, and the IUPUI Chancellor. He discusses his involvement in the dental profession and dental teaching. He also talks about the growth of IUPUI and his experiences there, and what it was like working under different administrations.
  Indiana University Medical Center; Indiana University School of Dentistry; IUPUI; Purdue University
  dental school dean; IUPUI chancellor; Oral Pathology and Periodontology chairperson
  Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  Indianapolis, Indiana
  dentistry; law school; university funding
- Holmquest, Stuart P. March 13, 1992, 91-087; 18 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 67 minutes; no index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Closed until March 13, 2017
  Stuart P. Holmquest received his undergraduate degree from Indiana University in 1937. After serving in the Navy during World War II, he went to work in the glass business. He eventually became chairman and chief executive officer of Brockway. Holmquest maintained his connection with Indiana University serving as an Indiana University Foundation member and as Advisory Council member. He discusses his undergraduate experiences at Indiana University, his service on Indiana University boards, the university's financial concerns, and the challenges facing minority and international students.
  Armstrong Cork Company; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University School of Business; Sigma Alpha Epsilon; Thatcher Glass Company; United Way of America
  chief executive officer; Indiana University Foundation member; navy gunnery officer
  Bryan, William Lowe; Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  clothing; contributions; fraternities; Great Depression; international students; minority groups; revenue; university funding; World War II
- Hudson, Herman April 10, 2001, 96-41; 29 pages; 2 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 120 minutes; pamplete on testimonial dinner for interviewee; interviewee resume; history of the Dept. of Afro-American studies; Marsh, Elisabeth
  Herman Hudson, 1923 - 2003, served as dean of Afro-Americans Affairs (1970 - 1981) and founded and chaired the Department of Afro-American Studies (1970 - 1972, 1981 - 1985). He discusses his educ++ation and teaching experience in Afghanistan prior to coming to IU. He explains how he established the department of Afro-American Studies, the recruiting of minority faculty, and efforts to build a Black Culture Center on campus. He discusses his retirement and continued interest in the Department of Afro-American studies.
  Columbia University; Indiana University; Kabul University; Neal Marshall Cultural Center; University of Michigan
  Afro-American studies professor; linguistics professor
  Klotman, Phyllis; Lowengrub, Morton; Maultsby, Portia; Point, John; Torchinsky, Alberto; Wiggins, William
  Afghanistan; Bloomington, Indiana
  affirmative action; African American students; Afro-American affairs; Afro-American studies; Afro-American studies faculty; enrollment; minority faculty; teaching
- Huffman, Vernon Richard September 18, 1991, 91-077; 14 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Vernon Huffman was born in Mooreland, Indiana, in 1914. He grew up and attended school in and near New Castle, Indiana, before coming to Indiana University in 1932. Huffman describes his involvement in college sports and fraternity and campus life. He also describes his career as a professional baseball player, manager of a dairy, and in the FBI. Subsequent to getting a law degree in 1940, Huffman continued his involvement in Indiana University with its alumni organizations.
  Beta Theta Pi; Detroit Lions; FBI; I-Men's Association; Indiana University Alumni Association; Johnson Creamery
  Huffman
  dairy manager; professional football player
  Bryan, William Lowe; Rich, Claude T.; Wells, Herman B
  baseball; basketball; college sports; football; fraternity hazing; Great Depression; professional football; student life
- Irvin, Glenn W. April 22, 1992, 91-095; 16 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 54 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Glenn Irwin attended Indiana University from 1938 to 1944, obtaining his undergraduate and medical degrees in only six years. He remained at Indiana University as a professor and administrator, serving as Dean of the Medical School, Chancellor of IUPUI, and vice president of Indiana University Indianapolis. He discusses his medical training, his administrative work, and the development of IUPUI.
  Indiana University Bloomington; Indiana University Hospital; Indiana University School of Medicine; IUPUI; Riley Hospital
  Indiana University Indianapolis vice president; IUPUI chancellor; medical professor; physician; School of Medicine dean
  Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Wells, Herman B
  endocrinology; medical education; medical school; World War II
- Jacobs, Barbara B. October 7, 1993, 91-203; 11 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips., 23 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Barbara Mae Jacobs, née Barrow, was born in Oak Park, Illinois, in 1926. She came to Indiana University in 1944 and graduated in 1948. She describes her education in home economics, her short career in education, and her family life in Cleveland, Ohio. She also describes her work on the board of the Indiana University Foundation, its fundraising efforts, and university funding in general. She also reflects on the greater role women have taken in politics and other areas of the public arena.
  Jacobs
  fundraiser; home economics teacher
  Weidman, Leah E.; Wells, Herman B
  foundation work; fundraising; home economics; university funding; women in politics; World War II veterans
- James, Daniel June 5, 1992, 91-115; 18 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 12 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Daniel James was born in Logansport, Indiana, in 1905. He earned a bachelor's degree at Indiana University from 1923 to 1926 and a law degree from 1926 to 1929. He describes his student days at Indiana University, memorable professors, his legal career in New York City after graduation, and his work with the Indiana University Foundation.
  Beekman and Bogue; Cotton and Franklin; Interborough Rapid Transit Company
  Carmichael, Hoagy; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Mendel, Bernardo; Patterson, Robert P.; Sandberg, Carl; Sembower, Charles J.; Senour, Frank; Wells, Herman B; Whiteman, Paul
  New York, New York; North Dakota
  cigarette smoking; college sports; formal wear; Great Depression; law firms; law school
- Jasper, Paul G. July 7, 1992, 91-120; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 35 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on December 15, 1908, Paul G. Jasper first came to Indiana University as an undergraduate in 1927 and earned his law degree in 1932. He speaks of his career as a attorney and, at one time, member of the Indiana Supreme Court. In addition, Jasper recalls the effects of the Great Depression on campus life. After service in World War II, he was again active in the Indiana University alumni association and the varsity club. He is also a member of the distinguished alumni association. Jasper played varsity football and basketball during his years as a student. Finally, he discusses the effects of financial difficulties at Indiana University.
  Bryan, William Lowe; Wells, Herman B
  Great Depression; student life; university funding; World War II
- Jennette, Noble S., III May 31, 1994, 91-265; 14 pages; 1 tape, 30 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Noble Stevenson Jennette III, born on May 20, 1953, attended Indiana University from 1974 through 1978, and completed his degree in 1980. A former student body president and United States Navy veteran, he was very active in campus politics and social issues. Jennette recalls student protests and anger over being cut out of the decision-making process at Indiana University. He speaks about the campus in the nineteen seventies and some of the leaders he had contact with including John Ryan, Robert O'Neil, and Steve Danzig.
  Danzig, Steve; O'Neil, Robert; Ryan, John W.
  campus politics; campus protests
- Johnson, Steve May 9, 1996, 96-010; 29 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Steve Johnson earned a masters degree in mathematics in 1972, a masters degree in computer science in 1977, and a Ph.D. in computer science in 1983, all at Indiana University. In 1984, he was hired to be a computer science professor at Indiana University. In this interview, Johnson speaks of the differences between the study of mathematics and computer science, the development of computer science and the Indiana University Department of Computer Science, and some problems that have occurred with this department. In addition, he cites some people who have influenced the university's Department of Computer Science including Dean Morton Lowengrub, Stu Shapiro, Mitchell Wand, and others.
  Indiana University Department of Computer Science
  computer science professor
  Friedman, Dan; Lowengrub, Morton; Prosser, Frank; Shapiro, Stu; Wand, Mitchell; Winkle, David
  computer science development; departmental problems; mathematics
- Jones, Frank B. February 6, 1992, 91-083; 23 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 102 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Frank B. Jones, born on April 3, 1923, came to Indiana University as a freshman in 1942 and, after three and a half years of service in the United States Army during World War II, returned to Indiana University to complete his undergraduate and graduate degrees. He then remained at the university to work in the alumni office for over forty years. In this interview, Jones speaks of his days as a student with regard to World War II and campus housing. In addition, he emphasizes the activities of the alumni office such as the organization of the Mini University, or alumni continuing education, and alumni family camps like Shawnee Bluffs. He also speaks of his association with Alice Nelson, Herman B Wells, and George Heighway, among many others.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; Mini University
  assistant alumni secretary
  Bryan, William Lowe; Franklin, Benjamin; Heighway, George "Dixie"; Homestead, Raleigh; Nelson, Alice; Rich, Claude T.; Wells, Herman B; Wright, Wendell W. "Whack"
  class reunions; Indiana University alumni family camp; international alumni; Northwest Ordinance Bicentennial; Shawnee Bluffs; student housing; university growth; World War II
- Kampen, Emerson November 22, 1991, 91-082; 14 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 40 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Emerson Kampen, born on March 12, 1928, is a graduate of the University of Michigan who was appointed to the Indiana University board of trustees and later, to the Purdue board of trustees. In this interview, he discusses the nature of his involvement with these two boards, and the similarities and differences between them. Kampen speaks of his reorganization of the Indiana University retirement plans and the garnering of funding in association with the Indiana University Foundation. In addition, he discusses his ideas on various political issues and political concerns.
  Indiana University Foundation; Purdue University
  environmental issues; fundraising; national politics; retirement plan